Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue
our series on NAD+,
an enzyme that is
found in all living things
and supposedly boosted
by a variety of supplements.
Lets look at nicotinamide.
Here’s our first story.
Ever since nicotinamide (NAM)
was also shown to cure pellagra,
both nicotinic acid, NA, and NAM have been
collectively referred to as niacin or vitamin B3,
though they are
distinct compounds.
For example, NAM is not plagued by
the same kind of hot flash reaction.
(Facial flushing attributed to
niacinamide in some older studies
was likely due to a less purified
form contaminated with residual NA.)
The relative capacity of NA versus
NAM to generate NAD+ is unclear.
Neither has been shown
to boost sirtuin activity,
but both do extend the
lifespan of C. elegans.
I couldn’t find any longevity
trials for NA in rodents;
however, NAM was put to the test
and failed to prolong the lives of mice.
What clinical effects might
we expect in people?
Previously, I explored the proven anti-
aging effects for topical nicotinamide
on the skin and the remarkable ability of
oral nicotinamide to help prevent skin cancer.
I also noted it failed to
prevent type 1 diabetes,
despite promising mouse data,
though it may help preserve
residual function in people
newly diagnosed with
type 1 diabetes,
but apparently not enough
to affect blood sugar control.
What about its use
as a NAD+ booster?
In those with
mitochondrial myopathy,
NA raised muscle NAD+ levels and
improved mitochondrial and muscle function,
but in healthy individuals,
muscle NAD+ levels didn’t budge.
However, the average age of individuals
in the control group was 50.
What about in older adults whose muscle
NAD+ levels might potentially be lower?
Four NAD+ precursors were tested
in older adults averaging in their 70s:
tryptophan, NA, NAM, and NR.
All four failed to improve
muscle strength or function,
failed to affect mitochondrial function,
and failed to even nudge
NAD+ levels in their muscles.
Why not give it a try anyway?
Again, side effects.
Like NA, high-dose NAM can cause
gastrointestinal disturbances
and signs of liver toxicity….
However, NAM may result in more
issues involving methylation.
The first step in breaking down excess
NAM is to transfer a methyl group to it,
forming methylnicotinamide.
Unfortunately,
methylnicotinamide is neurotoxic
and can cross the
blood-brain barrier.
This may explain why NAM can exacerbate
Parkinson’s-like symptoms in rats
and why Parkinson’s patients
have higher levels
of the NAM-methylating
enzyme in their brains.
And the same with Alzheimer's
brains for that matter.
Excess NAM may also deplete
the body’s pool of methyl groups.
If you read the Epigenetics chapter
in my book How Not to Age,
you may remember that DNA methylation is
critical for the regulation of gene expression.
Epigenetic changes caused by
NAM-induced methyl depletion
have been blamed as the reason
why rats fed megadoses of NAM
suffer from fatty livers
and swollen kidneys,
but that was at a human-equivalent dose
far exceeding what people might take.
Is there any evidence that
more modest NAM supplementation
might affect methylation in humans?
Yes, and even with a single
dose as low as 100 mg.
Methylation also plays a key role in
breaking down fight-or-flight hormones
like noradrenaline and neurotransmitters
like serotonin and histamine.
Within hours of a single
100 mg dose of NAM,
blood levels of all three
become elevated,
suggesting their metabolism was impaired
by the shunting of methyl groups
to deal with the excess NAM.
Also noted was a significant
rise in homocysteine,
which is a byproduct of
methylation reactions
and a risk factor for cardiovascular
disease and dementia.
Another potential problem with NAM
is that it’s a sirtuin inhibitor.
Wait, I thought the whole purpose of taking
NAD+ precursors is to boost sirtuin activity.
Sirtuin enzymes use up
NAD+ and spit out NAM.
This allows the body to recycle the NAM
back into NAD+ for further sirtuin use.
But it also means the body can use
NAM as part of a negative feedback loop.
Like a thermostat in the winter
that shuts down the furnace
when there’s too much heat,
the body shuts down NAD+ use by
sirtuins when it detects too much NAM.
NAM pills didn’t exist
when our bodies evolved;
so, in the wake of a
sudden wave of NAM,
the body must think its sirtuins are
churning out too much and dials them back.
Perhaps, this explains why NAM
fails to prolong the lifespans of mice.
When the sirtuin-suppressing effects of
NAM were first reported 20 years ago,
the researchers cautioned that
this could potentially lead to
“deleterious consequences of long-term
nicotinamide therapy in humans.”
In our next story, we look at how the
suppression of NAD+ synthesis
by a purported NAD booster
called NR in humans
may explain the disparate rodent results.
NR and NMN seem to be more promising
NAD+ precursors than NA or NAM,
since they don’t cause flushing
nor do they directly inhibit sirtuins.
In mice, NR and NMN both
raised liver NAD+ levels,
but of the two, only NR significantly
raised NAD+ in the muscles.
Also, NR is so far the only NAD+ booster
shown to prolong the lifespan of mice.
There have been at least
10 clinical trials of NR,
most showing it can boost human
blood levels of NAD+ by up to 168%.
Note, though, that most doses
used exceeded 300 mg,
which is the daily dose
approved as safe
by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration
and European Food Safety Authority.
At the approved dose, blood NAD+ is
boosted more on the order of 50 to 60%,
but no dose was found to affect NAD+ levels
in human muscle (compared to placebo).
The greater preponderance
of human bioavailability
and safety data for
NR compared to NMN
has led some to proclaim NR
as the preferred NAD+ precursor.
And, by some, I mean employees
of a chemical company
that produces NR for supplements.
The question after all
of these human NR trials
is have any of them
shown clinical benefit?
Sadly, no.
Let’s go through the alphabet.
After accounting for
multiple testing,
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials of NR
in middle-aged or older adults failed to find
any significant benefit over placebo
for artery stiffness or
artery function, BAT activation,
blood pressure, blood sugar control,
body weight,
cardiac energy or ejection fraction,
fat burning,
fatty liver, exercise capacity,
fatigue,
insulin sensitivity,
metabolic flexibility,
metabolic health,
metabolic rate,
mitochondrial function
or biogenesis,
muscle blood flow, upper
or lower body muscle strength,
pancreatic function or the
release of metabolic hormones,
the treatment of Parkinson’s disease
symptoms, or physical performance.
NR-hawking companies claim
NR is anti-inflammatory,
but in their own study, only 3 out of 10
markers of inflammation were affected
compared to placebo,
and a subsequent independent study
using the same dose for twice as long
found zero of 12 markers affected.
Remarkably, the opposite was found for
many of these outcomes in rats and mice.
In rodents, NR does raise
NAD+ levels in muscle,
improving insulin sensitivity
and mitochondrial biogenesis,
and on down much of the list.
Why does NR work in rodents but
appear to almost entirely flop in people?
Some have suggested
inadequate dosing.
The typical dose used
in mouse studies
Was about twice that used
in many human studies,
but a double dose has been
tried in people, to no avail.
Another possibility is sirtuin inhibition by NAM,
the main degradation product of NR.
In fact, based on mouse studies,
NR may metabolize in the gut into NAM or
NA before it even makes it in the bloodstream.
Either way, unlike in mice,
NR can’t seem to elevate
NAD+ in human muscle;
so, no wonder there’s no alteration
of human sirtuin activity.
Maybe that explains
the disparate results.
In fact, the key NAD+ synthesizing
enzyme in human muscle biopsies
was actually suppressed
by NR supplementation.
This doesn’t happen in mice,
but it does in people.
Presumably this downregulation
is an adaptive response
to the unnaturally large flood
of NR coming into the system.
So, what happens when you
stop taking the supplement?
How quickly does your enzyme
activity bounce back?
In mice, not only may
their microbiome affect NR,
but the NR may affect
their microbiome, too.
Some of the benefits of NR
can then be transferred
between mice via
fecal transplants.
So, at least in mice,
some of the benefits of NR
may be due to modulating
the mouse microbiome.
The distinct differences between the
gut flora of humans and rodents
may offer another explanation why
NR works in them, but not us.
Unlike NAM, supplementation with
NR did not increase homocysteine levels,
but one study of a combination of NR
plus a resveratrol analogue called pterostilbene
raised LDL cholesterol high enough to kill
as many as 1 in 40 long-term users.
However, this effect is presumed
to be due to the pterostilbene,
as NR alone has not been shown to raise LDL,
whereas pterostilbene has.
One study did find that NR seems to
cause a small reduction in hematocrit,
hemoglobin, and platelet count in
people within a week of starting it.
This shift towards a
more anemic state
was suggested to account for impaired
exercise performance seen in rats given NR.
However, the 35% drop in performance
did not reach statistical significance.
NR did cause a significant increase
in systemic oxidative stress, however,
and another rodent study
found a worsening of inflammation
and deterioration of
metabolic health,
but if positive effects in rodents
don’t translate to people,
perhaps we shouldn’t expect
that negative ones will either.
Regulatory authorities
from Australia, Canada,
Europe, and the United States
have all authorized NR as safe,
at least up to 300mg a day
(or 230 in pregnant and lactating women).
But the lack of demonstrable clinical benefit
would seem to preclude NR supplementation.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.